# Marat Garafutdinov

1003 NW 65<sup>th</sup> St Seattle, WA 98117 Cell: (425) 444-2204 • Email: maratoid@gmail.com • http://www.maratg.com

### **About**

I am a seasoned software developer with an interest in automation, continuous delivery, deployment and mobile application development.

I have extensive real-world business experience and an excellent track record in gathering, analyzing and defining business and functional requirements. I am experienced in designing and implementing complex software solutions with emphasis on customer satisfaction, quality and timely delivery.

### **Skills**

- C/C++, Java, Ruby, Android; \*nix/Windows platforms; CI/CD tools
- Experience with various PaaS/laaS solutions
- Familiarity with most current versioning and defect tracking systems
- Experience with agile and formal software development lifecycle methodologies and practices.
- 14+ years of software development and program management experience.

# **Experience**

### DevOps engineer at MTN Satellite Communications.

July 2013 - October 2014

- Designed and implemented test and integration tools for MTN CI pipeline.
- Created a set of scripts/utilities for modeling a MTN ShipCloud™ in AWS.
- Improved reliability, speed and scalability of MTN CI/CD pipeline.
- Developed and improved a variety of internal Chef cookbooks.

#### Android Apps Developer at MTN Satellite Communications.

February 2013 - July 2013

- Designed and implemented client-customizable Android front-ends for a variety of MTN on-ship services.
- Designed and implemented an rspec-based functional testing framework for the MTN on-ship application suite.
- Designed and implemented a concurrency and stress testing framework for the MTN on-ship application suite.

### Consultant at StarSightings Inc.

October 2010 - Present

Created first version of StarSightings for Android.

#### Software Design Engineer at Microsoft.

July 2012 - February 2013

- Implemented new features of Ford SYNCII project, including HMI and middle layer.
- Did sustained engineering for Ford SYNC project, including field problem investigations and backporting of features from Ford SYNC II.

Marat Garafutdinov Page 1 of 3

Worked directly with Ford and Elektrobit employees to investigate and resolve field bug reports.

# Co-Founder, Engineering at TravellingWave Inc.

May 2007 - July 2012

TravellingWave develops multimodal interfaces for entering speech into mobile devices. Using a combination of speech recognition and text prediction dubbed "VoicePredict," TravellingWave's technology enhances any kind of text input mechanism and allows for fast, easy and accurate data entry.

- Performed engineering duties throughout all phases of software development lifecycle of VoicePredict SDK for ARM/X86 devices and SMS/Email/Facebook/Twitter client for Windows Mobile 6.x.
- Drove development effort from the start, including design and time estimations including design, time estimations and most of the coding.
- Contributed to and implemented interfaces for TravellingWave proprietary noise filtering algorithm.
- Designed and implemented instrumentation system for gathering anonymous user feedback.
- Designed and implemented VoicePredict SMS/Email/Facebook/Twitter client for Windows Mobile 6.x.
- Designed, implemented and maintained company's website.

# Software Design Engineer at Cisco Systems

July 2010 - December 2011

- Developed 1.0 version of Connect Express an iOS/Android application for controlling a wide range of Cisco/Linksys WiFi routers remotely. For iOS and Android.
- Developed a software/hardware installer application for an upcoming home networking product on OS X and Windows platforms.
- Designed and implemented a localization/internationalization system for Cisco's upcoming home networking product.
- Worked on parts of Webkit/QT based UI for various product components
- Maintained build system for the product.

### Software Design Engineer at Intrinsyc Software, USA

May 2006 - May 2007

Intrinsyc Software's Soleus is world's first Microsoft Windows Embedded CE-based mobile handset platform, featuring pre-integrated hardware, software and telephony elements.

- Designed and developed from the ground up a full-featured custom shell for Soleus platform, with support for notifications, custom/animated icons, configurable "today" screen, multiple page layouts and tight integration with other system components.
- Worked on various other platform applications, such as calendar, alarm notifications, etc.

# Software Design Engineer at Microsoft

September 2005 – May 2006

- Ported and enhanced an existing test harness for the Windows Vista Tablet Edition.
- Worked on the design and development of a web-based system for running ink tests remotely.

# Software Design Engineer at Conversay Inc.

April 2001 – September 2005

- Designed and implemented Conversay's speech enabled forms automation software for Windows Desktop, including creating functional and design specifications.
- Managed and led two offshore teams developing the Windows Mobile version of the forms automation client and the XML form builder.
- Designed and developed proofs of concept and pilot projects for General Electric Power Division.

Marat Garafutdinov Page 2 of 3

- Ported parts of Conversay's speech recognition SDK to MontaVista HardHat Linux, for deployment on a portable GPS device. Contributed to Conversay's speech recognition SDK and engine development.
- Developed parts of Conversay's suite of PIM applications.
- Designed and developed internationalization and localization components for deployment on Samsung phone ROMs.

### Configuration Management Engineer at Conversay Inc.

September 2000 – April 2001

- Designed and developed multiple CM tools, supervised VSS configuration and daily builds.
- Helped design, implement and manage Conversay's proprietary defect tracking tool.

# **Education and Achievements**

University of Washington (September 1998 – November 2001): Applied and Computational Mathematical Sciences (Applied Math, Statistics, Computer Science) program.

Patents: Multimodal interface for input of text (20100031143). Detecting segments of speech from an audio stream (20100100382).

Marat Garafutdinov Page 3 of 3